Alright friends, in this video we start talking about inheritance, which is one of the core
principles of object oriented programming, not just Java, and this is something which
again will take from scratch because it has to have a good solid understanding for this
feature to be used almost at all places, whatever you would do, you would be indirectly
working with inheritance, whether you do it explicitly yourself or not, right?
So again, we'll just take up a real world analogy and I told you in the video where we
were talking the object oriented programming principles about inheritance and how it allows
us enables us to do reusability of code, right?
So let's just take that example, that legendary example, which I always taken of the class
human and see how inheritance plays a part.
So for example, you have this class human, right?
And what do we have inside human?
For example, if we just talk about the methods, what can every human do and know that this
is again, just the idea, not the object because I'm just talking about the idea of human,
the class.
That is humans obviously can eat, right?
And they can walk, they can run, they can smile, they can breathe and do all those things
that every human can, right?
Just put this in a scat, all right?
And now there was another another class, for example, another idea, which took this idea
forward, right, and that was the idea of, let me just put this here, let's think about
it, and that is the idea of a class that came in and it was called Ranjit, all right.
So now this idea of Ranjit, Ranjit obviously is a human, right?
How do you know that because Ranjit does this?
So the arrow is shown in reverse in inheritance, that means when Ranjit inherits human, right?
We say the relationship is called is an object oriented design philosophy terms.
It's called is a, now we say Ranjit is a human true because it is inheriting from
human, and the moment it inherits from human, it now has the copy of eat, walk, run, smile
and breathe in Ranjit as well, and the beauty is as if they were Ranjit's own properties.
But just at the time when I'm explaining this idea to you, think about it in real world
terms, just try to imagine that in your mind, that is what I'm saying, that is there
is a human class, which all of us inherit, which all of our classes inherit in the real
world.
Because all mighty had to find somewhere that humans can eat, walk, run, smile and
breathe that and do all those things that every human can, that means we can as well
why?
Because we are inheriting from that class and the moment Ranjit does this as I said, in addition
to these five properties, Ranjit now can have its own properties as well, right?
And a lot, rewrite them here because they're invisibly in Ranjit as well, right?
And just say, just put this like this, right?
You'll find the same properties, right?
If these five properties, but Ranjit can have its own properties as well, that's one
of the beautiful parts of inheritance that is, see, in this case, we say, human becomes
the parent class, Ranjit becomes the child class, there is always a parent and a child.
And in Java terms, we appropriately say, human is a super class, Ranjit is the subclass
and the subclass inherits the properties from the super type, right?
So human is the super type, Ranjit is the subtype here, right?
And the beautiful thing as I said, Ranjit can now go on and have its own properties as well.
But Ranjit did not take the choice, Ranjit wanted to be an ordinary human who could
eat, walk, run, smile and breathe, and that's perfectly fine to live our lives.
Sometimes we overcomplicate, right?
We don't need to, but on the other hand, there was another class that came in here.
And that was, for example, this time, let's just put in a random name and that is Shweta.
And now Shweta, what she did is she also inherited from human.
That means she is also, now I say, Shweta is a human true, right?
And the moment Shweta did that.
So what happened is, you know, now the properties of human will now be accessible inside
Shweta as well as if they are her own properties.
But Shweta, Ranjit has a choice that is she can have her own properties and this time
in addition to just being eaten, walking, running, smiling, and breathing, Shweta thought
that I would be an extraordinary human because I would have a property that is not there
in other humans.
And Ranjit cannot dance, but that's perfectly fine to live.
Shweta can do, eat walk runs while breathing, I can also dance that makes her a unique
property in Shweta that's perfectly fine.
And it still is, you know, you just think about it in the real world terms as I'm saying.
So that means this is what we called inheritance super class, subtype, super type, subtype,
right?
And this concept of a super class and a sub class, right, a sub class inherits the properties
of the human.
And now let's look at Shweta and Ranjit, right?
Do they also share a relationship inheritance relationship ship or any relationship here?
No, just because they are siblings from the same parent, right?
It just happens to be they are siblings from the same parent, but between them, they do
not have any inheritance relationship.
You cannot access Ranjit's property properties in Shweta, nor can you access Shweta
as property the other way round in Ranjit, right?
That's how it works.
And this type of inheritance, now there are types when it is, this is called single
level inheritance, where there is a super type and there is a sub class, right?
Super class, subclass, subclass, subclass, this is called single level inheritance.
But there is another one that is multi level.
How does this work?
That is for example, there was one more class here and that is that came down the line
and that was called, for example, now mean now, now mean did this.
That means now mean is a subclass of Ranjit, Ranjit is a subclass of human.
That means in now mean you will find the properties of Ranjit as well as of human and Ranjit
can have their own properties as well.
This level of inheritance, this type of inheritance is called multi level inheritance.
That is, there is a super class, then a subclass and then a subclass, but Shweta and human,
this still is single level inheritance.
And then there was one more that is, when sometimes what happens is a subclass has more
than one super classes, right?
There is a subclass which is derived, which is inherited from more than one subclass, super
classes, it's called multi pull inheritance, which is not permissible in Java.
This level of inheritance is not permissible in Java.
That is multiple inheritance, right?
Cannot happen, but we have a way around, we have a workaround, I'll just walk you through
about that in some time in a different video, but for now know that Java supports single
level, multi level, not multiple inheritance directly.
It supports directly, indirectly we'll talk about that, but that is just a good understanding
of what inheritance is.
In the next video, we'll just dive in to our ID and take this idea, the subtract idea
of the human or any other thing that comes to you might see, I just draw the idea of human
and Ranjit and Shweta and Naminin, you can go ahead and on your whiteboard, on your notebook,
on your tab, what you can do is just think about any idea that you can map to inheritance.
That is for example, as I said, it can be a phone and smartphone, it can be a television
and then different televisions, how they inherit from the basic idea.
This is inheritance, right?
Just draw that out before I walk you through the core in how do we go about doing all
of this through core and intelligent in Java.